have you ever thought about how fat loss
happens I don't mean what you do to lose
weight over time in other words diet and
exercise whatever that means I mean
what's the physiology of fat loss how is
it you can be like my friend vau here
who weighed 210 lbs and a few months
later only weighs 170 lb now we're not
going to talk about what he did to
achieve that fat loss in other words his
diet program or his workout program what
we're going to talk about in this series
or in this video is what actually
happened physiologically that allowed
that weight loss to occur why is it he
implemented or he put into the Earth 210
pounds of pressure now all of a sudden
he puts only 170 pounds of pressure
another way to think about this is how
is it that he literally occupied this
much space in the world right he used to
be out to here now he's only out to here
how did did he
physiologically rid his body of that
extra
space in this episode of 55 minute
physiology we're going to dive hard into
the paint on fat loss we'll talk about
the actual physiology and a little bit
of the biochemistry of it we'll talk
about the training implications some
Diet implications and the reason I want
to do this video is because once you
understand the foundation or the
physiology of it you'll understand which
Training Method is most effective what
type of diet you should do and what to
do when you can present it with new
information or when clients ask you
things like hey this is what I want to
do for fat loss will this work or more
importantly I heard this is how it works
I heard this is what's going on I heard
I should do this program because this
reason is this true so that's what we're
going to answer in this series now as
you're going to start noticing from the
55 minute physiology series some of
these things are not necessarily 55
minutes some of them are 35 minutes and
in this case it's probably going to be
more like a couple of hours so we'll
split it up into multiple parts so we
can really understand what's happening
with the physiology of fat
loss so how is it my friend V here lost
all of that
fat
specifically how did it get off of his
body how did he rid himself of that fat
around his neck and his ears and his
fingers and his back pad because we all
hate that nasty fat back
right how is
it I mean I want you to think about
right now take a second to consider how
is it physiologically possible that his
body got that stuff off of
him did he maybe pee out all that fat
well you actually do pee out a tiny
little bit of it but that's not really
it someone who's going through dramatic
fat loss like that didn't just have a
lot of fatty pee over months and
months did he maybe poop it out well
again turns out if you well anyone
that's actually ate in a extremely high
fat diet uh when they weren't used to it
can tell you that you can definitely
poop out some fat
but that's not again what we're talking
about he didn't just poop a lot more
over three months or whatever it was did
he sweat it out well it turns out
long-term fat loss is not a result of
sweat now of course you can lose a bunch
of weight very acutely especially in the
case of someone like an MMA fighter or a
wrestler can dehydrate themselves really
quickly they can lose a bunch of weight
but as soon as you drink water back
again those numbers are going to come
right back to the middle you're not
actually losing fat that way you might
lose some weight on the scale for a few
minutes but it's not really fat
so if I don't pee it out I don't poop it
out and I don't sweat it out how do I
get it
out well I need you to do something for
me hopefully you're not driving while
you're listening to this hopefully
you're sitting somewhere and if you can
I want you to go ahead and do the
following on the count of three I want
you to take a big deep breath in one two
3 congratulations you all just got a
little bit skinnier you can send your
checks in the mail right on over I'm
your personal dietitian and personal
trainer that's right fat loss happens
through
respiration you or in the case of our
friend V here had extremely fatty breath
for a long
time make sense I don't think so we got
to go into the details a little bit more
how is it that I can lose fat by
breathing now some of you are very
clever out there and you're probably
thinking wait a minute if that's
true could I just lose a bunch of weight
by and just panting like my dog ghost
face no right actually it's true that's
exactly what you do that is exactly how
fat loss happens oh my gosh right
somebody go ahead and put it out there
on Instagram new fat loss hack just
breathe right well it's kind of true and
it's not true because what would happen
if you just sat there and
went if you hyperventilate you're
probably going to pass out or get really
laded but can you think of a situation
in which your respiration rate is
elevated but you're not passing
out it's exercise right which is sort of
funny because if we go back to the
beginning and we talk about our very
basic prescription for fat loss diet and
exercise right well in one one respect
that is as B spefic specific as you need
to get because all you really do have to
do is some form of exercise that makes
you breathe you do it enough if you do
it long enough and if you're patient
enough it's going to technically
work well in order to really understand
this we need to dive a little bit into
the biochemistry and the physiology of
what's Happening Here Now to understand
how breathing makes you lose fat we've
got to zoom in all the way down to the
level of the individual atom up here in
the corner what we have to understand is
your basic
macronutrients okay now in our our
context the only macronutrients we're
going to talk about are carbohydrates
fat and protein there's a couple more
but this is the most part what we're
concerned about if I use our piece of
bread here or our bun to represent
carbohydrate I'll use this cheese to
represent fat now I know that there's
some protein and fat but don't get lost
in the woods
here we'll use this this burger here the
meat to represent protein I know there's
fat in there but just don't worry about
it right so we've got one picture to
represent our individual macronutrients
what most people don't necessarily
realize is that all of these
macronutrients for the most part have
the same molecular makeup and
specifically what we're talking about
here are the fat and the carbohydrates
both of these molecules are long chains
of carbon in other words they are
hundreds if not Millions probably of
individual carbon atoms attached
together to make a big long chain of
carbon now in the case of carbohydrate
specifically when we talk about glucose
which is one of the simple forms of
carbohydrate that is a six carbon chain
all right fat has a different structure
it's got usually three carbon chain
backbone and then it's got individual
chains alongside of it which we call
fatty acids and those chains are simply
big long chains of carbon with each one
having anywhere between like six and 20
carbons on it so for one molecule of
carbohydrate we typically have six
carbons of available but for one
molecule of fat we have you know 20 30
40 carbons right protein is a little bit
different in fact it's not a major
player in energy metabolism so we're not
going to worry about it too much it does
have some associated with it but it's a
little bit different we'll talk about
that in other
videos okay so if we're looking about
looking at these carbon chains now what
we also have to remember is whether I'm
talking about food in this particular
case that you consume or I'm talking
about the actual food already in you
it's the same thing
remember if we're talking about a piece
of cheese or a a hamburger as being
food all that means is it's another
animal we're making food just like
another animal could make me food right
so we're talking about the fat on your
stomach or the fat on your plate it's
the same damn thing right this used to
be someone else's bicep or glutes right
used to be other animals and we made it
food but they could tear us to Pieces
put us on a grill and we would be the
same thing right so I'm saying that to
say that what we're talking about here
I'm using a picture for in this
particular case of actual food well if I
change that picture to be something like
this this is 5 pounds of human fat and 5
pounds of human muscle same thing right
so whether we're talking about hey I
want to lose some fat on my body I've
got love handles out to here I want to
lose them the physiology or the
mechanics of the chemistry anyways are
the same to burn that pack or that big
chunk of fat as it is to burn the fat I
eat in my stomach okay so we don't have
to get lost in those mechanics very much
so as a general overview again we've got
these molecules that are big long chains
of carbon now in the case of human
metabolism what happens is we go to the
end of that chain and we snap break off
one of those carbon molecules now in
this particular case the amount of
energy I had to put into the
system is less than the amount of energy
I get out of the system so that's a net
positive result in energy gain right I
put a little bit of work in to break the
bond but I got way more energy out after
I broke it boom I get energy in the case
again of Ex human exercise physiology
will then use that energy to produce
things like exercise and movement
whatever it happens to
be but then we're left with a bit of a
predicament we've got this free floating
carbon around your body doesn't like
that essentially or almost effectively
what it does is create an acidic
environment and so your body says okay
we just did this we gained energy
because you told us you needed energy to
climb that wall or to pick up that stone
or to you know push that rower up and
down or whatever you're doing but you
caused this to have this free floating
carbon around what are you going to do
about it you got to get it out of here
right it's that drunk friend at the bar
get this guy out of here well your body
says well you know what I I I know this
guy is drunk and he's an embarrassment
to everyone he's really irritating he's
annoying but he does have a friend who
will come pick him up let's call his
buddy
O2 right oxygen or O2 is what's floating
around in the environment and so you
have broken this bond in your body now
you've got this free floating carbon
around and then you do
this and you take a big deep breath in
and you bring in a bunch of o2 right so
we introduce O2 into the
environment right that O2 will then bind
to the carbon forming carbon dioxide we
then
go and exhale
and rid ourselves of the carbon so to
recap everything we did we put we put
took a big deep breath in brought in O2
broke off our carbon molecule from our
fat pad took that carbon bound it to the
O2 we just inhaled and then got it out
of our body in the form of carbon
dioxide that carbon dioxide has a
physical real life measurable weight and
so the amount of weight I lose is
directly equal to the amount of carbons
I exhale
this whole process of breaking these
carbon bonds to give us energy is what
we call
metabolism right we've all heard of
people that have a fast metabolism or
slow metabolism it's really the same
speed in everyone but some of us just
are more active have a more Active
Metabolism or less Active Metabolism but
this is all we're really talking about
now if you take a chemistry class or a
biochemistry or even an exercise
physiology class you'll learn about the
minutia of Mak the energy from those
breaking of those carbon bonds cuz it is
a little bit different but at the
surface level that's really all we're
talking
about since we just rid ourselves of one
carbon dioxide molecule the length of
our carbon chains whether this again be
our fat stores or our carbohydrate
stores the length of those got smaller
so you can see that being depicted in
our picture up
here they get shorter if I were to
continue this process again so do
something else that required energy I
would cut off another carbon dioxide
it'll bind to some more O2 as long as I
keep breathing and the length of that
thing will keep getting shorter and
shorter so all I need to do is put
myself in a place where I have a net
greater energy demand than I have energy
availability so I do something arbitrary
like go for a run lift some weights
throw some kettle bells around that
tells my body give me some energy it
breaks some bonds com combines with O2
we breathe it out our fat pad and sugar
pads get
smaller so that's all we're really
looking at without getting into too much
detail here and we'll get into some
later with metabolism but what we're
really saying here is the net end
product of all your macronutrient
metabolism is O2 excuse me
CO2 ATP and water so the pictures I'm
using to represent it down here right
whether we're talking about carbohydrate
all of the carbohydrate in your body
when you fully metabolizes metabolize it
it ends as only three things carbon
dioxide which you breathe out
water which you use and this molecule
called ATP that's it the same thing with
fat or protein for that matter once you
finish metabolizing all three of these
macronutrients there's only three
possible options and it will be the same
every damn
time they're all working together to
make this same ATP molecule which some
of us call the energy currency of your
body the ATP molecules what you actually
do to make the energy and it's the only
option you have physiologically there is
no other way to make biological energy
other than making
ATP so I use this to tell you when we
start thinking about this and we start
trying to answer questions from clients
or from parents or for yourself when we
start saying things like well what is
the best way to B to burn fat or what is
the best diet to lose
fat right what type of workout should I
do to maximize fat burning what we have
to realize is okay you know what all of
it is coming out as CO2 so your answer
to that question is this look anything
that simply makes you breathe or
enhances your rate of respiration will
make you lose weight now in some of our
other classes we will talk about how
some systems are a little bit more
efficient um some are better at
adherence but what we're really talking
about here is I will guarantee you one
thing 100% money back if you're trying
to lose
fat if you put yourself on a training
program that you like so actually let me
restart this trainers coaches if you're
working with an athlete the sing single
most important variable you can do for
someone who's trying to lose weight is
make sure you can maximize
adherence in other words put them on a
program that they will do the most and
that they will work the hardest at so
for some of your clients that may mean
you have to put them on an elliptical
for 30 minutes a day some of your
clients that may mean never ever do a
30-minute run right design them a
workout that they like that they will
work the hardest at and that they will
stay with because anything that makes
them breathe will make them lose weight
right so they have the option say um
just to make up numbers and these
numbers are not right but it gives the
idea say in order to lose one pound of
fat you have to take 500
exhales again those numbers are way off
I'm just making a point here now you can
choose to do your 500 over the course of
an hour if you wanted to go for like say
a very light jog your respiration would
go up a little bit right instead of
breathing at this normal Pace 10 breaths
a minute maybe
you well I would get to 500 eventually
might take me an hour though right but
500 is 500 or maybe I decide to help
with it I don't want to waste an hour
I'd rather go Sprint up that hill or
that mountain as fast as I can make my
breath do
this and it would maybe take me 10
minutes to get 500 in as opposed to an
hour well chemically it doesn't matter a
whole lot again that's not to say those
training programs are
identical but they probably differ a lot
less than they are similar so when
you're talking about working with your
athletes your clients find what they
like to do what they will work the
hardest at and what they will do the
most frequently that's what's going to
get you the best long-term success for
someone who's not say a professional
athlete who doesn't have endless
resources we need to jump in a little
bit more and start talking about the
sources of cellular energy so in other
words back to those macronutrients how
do I actually go from a piece of car
carbohydrate or a piece of fat that I
ate my piece of fat here and produce
cellular energy so that I can power
exercise and power human movement or
anything else I need energy for okay as
a quick analogy or a quick way to think
about this what I want you to do is
think about the four sources of energy
in your body now again this is a quick
overview this is not every single thing
but this is the vast majority of what
you need to know your three macron which
we've already talked about but I also
want to talk about phosphocreatine now
it in of itself is not an actual ual
macronutrient if you watch the 5minute
physiology video on this you've already
heard me discuss that but I like to
think of it as a macronutrient because
it makes it makes more sense the way
that we we process it and use it to
produce energy now right away like I
mentioned before all of these things are
coming together to try to make the same
molecule ATP ATP stands for Denine
triphosphate which we can you can see
here one two three triphosphate it's got
three phosphate molecules attached to
this adenosine thing
well as I mentioned uh we'll talk
perhaps later videos about protein as a
fuel source but generally we like to use
protein as structure or Building
Material not necessarily fuel so let's
just go ahead and take that off the list
for now so we canot get too worried
about it and we'll talk about our three
primary fuel sources fats carbohydrate
and phosphor creatine as I mentioned
they're all trying to make ATP once we
have ATP we can then split that ATP into
what's called a DP so you've gone from
adenosine triphosphate to adenosine
diphosphate you can see that phosphate
that inorganic phosphate is in floating
around free that net result right there
just like when we broke the carbon Bond
right that gives us a net result of
energy right in fact it also gives us a
bunch of heat and depending on who you
ask something like 60 to 70 so per of
the energy produced from that reaction
will result actually in heat not
necessarily energy but nonetheless all
right that that's why you actually get
hot that's why you warm up when you
exercise a lot but whatever remaining
energy is available we will use that to
power things like human exercise right
so you see me there on Tory Pines
crushing it on probably I think the I
think that was probably the first hole
if that's the hole I actually put it in
the bunker far into the left and then I
had to chip way out into the other
bunker actually another Fairway Deep
Woods and then I hit like a 200 yard
shot out of the deeps on the onto the
green over top of a bunker then put it
in for part was incredible right I'm not
a great golfer so that was amazing to
par the first Hol toic Pines anyways
right so we're trying to use that power
energy to power exercise or whatever
else we want to do physically uh whether
we need to grow new immune cells we need
to produce red blood cells we need to
communicate um your brain astrocytes
your nerve nervous system your red blood
cells themselves go through anob
metabolism so whatever it is we need to
do at this point I want to take a little
bit of a pause and go hard into some
bioenergetics so those of you that have
had a little bit of exercise phys
physiology I think you'll really like
this next section because we're going to
try to cover all everything you learned
in exercise physiology and do it once
over every slide if you haven't had it I
think this is actually going to be
really exciting to you because you're
going to see and and a lot of things
you're going to click and go oh yeah
that's why so take a deep breath if you
have to go grab a drink of water refill
the coffee um whatever you need to do
put yourself together mentally because
this is going to be a little bit of a of
a a dive here into this next section
which is what I call the summary of all
bioenergetics
all righty here we go let's dive in
let's assume you had a big meal okay now
it doesn't necessarily matter what that
meal is but let's just say it was a
mixed macronutrient meal so in this
particular case a delicious hamburger
with uh you'll have some fat in this
meal you have some carbohydrate and some
protein well that's going to actually
sit in your gut as an actual piece of of
food right but by the time it leaves
your gut and gets into your blood it's
no longer in these macronutrient form or
sorry no long longer in this food form
it's actually broken down all the way
into its macronutrient components so in
other words if I draw your blood I don't
get I don't see oh you ate a hamburger I
just see oh my gosh blood sugar's gone
way up there's a lot of fat in the blood
there's a lot of protein in the blood
all right so the first step that
actually happens is your gut breaks down
that food into those individual
macronutrients and it sort of separates
them out now as we showed earlier that
will release an excessive amount of
energy depending in fact the amount of
energy released is differs between those
macronutrients but you will get a little
bit of usable energy that you can then
from there go on to either produce ATP
or it'll come out as
heat okay and if we start with
carbohydrate first and I'm going to do
this because I think it's the most
important it's the most prevalent again
remember in your blood the blood glucose
floating around in your system is in the
six carbon chain form so you got six
carbons floating around and I don't care
that you know that necessarily but I'm I
want you to pay attention to these
carbon counting because it'll make sense
that the very end I promise in fact this
entire 55 minute physiology series will
make sense if you pay attention to the
carbon counting now so we got six
carbons there which I'm representing and
I think there's six in that pack from
there I'm going to go through a process
called glycolysis now it is exactly what
it sounds gly meaning gly glucose
glucose or glycogen which is the stored
form of sugar and Lis anytime you hear
the word Lis that means to break apart
so glycolysis quite literally is the
metabolic process of breaking apart
glucose or
glycogen as a result of that again we
broke more bonds right those carbon
chains we broke off we will get some
things that we were able to use to
produce ATP and we'll get this other
molecule nadh which we'll talk about in
a little bit later now what actually
happens is that that glucose molecule if
you picture it to be a six carbon
molecule gets actually split up into two
separate three carbon molecules called
pyruvate in your image here I'm only
showing one pyruvate but in reality
there's actually two so we just split it
apart know we didn't lose any carbon
dioxide yet we just took a six carbon
molecule split in half each one of those
three carbon molecules though will get
then further split into a molecule
called acet or acetyl COA now those
molecules are actually only two carbon
things so you'll notice we went from six
to two sets of three down to two sets of
two we lost two carbons right
here right and so there we go there we
have immediately lost ourselves two
carbons and we're only just started the
process of breaking down
a
carbohydrate the acety coase that you
form those two carbon molecules will
then go through a process called that
I'm labeling TCA here which people often
refer to as the citric acid cycle or uh
the KB cycle and each one of those two
carbon molecules will get its own
individual Spin and they'll go through
and as a result of that you'll make a
bunch more ATP you'll make some of these
nadh molecules but more importantly you
get a net result of two carbon dioxide
molecules per turn
turn all right so to wrap that whole
thing together when I talk about
carbohydrate metabolism or glucose
metabolism I start with a six carbon
molecule I break it down into two three
carbon molecules each one of those gets
broken down into two two carbon
molecules I exhale two carbon dioxides
this gets a turn to the KB cycle which n
results me in two carbon dioxides and
then this gets a turn and I have two
carbon dioxides so I'm left with no
carbon I metabolized carb carbohydrate I
got left with ATP
water and some carbon dioxide that I
breathe out as waste down
here if I have sufficient O2
available the things that are left over
at the end of the KB cycle will then go
onto a thing called the electron
transport chain I'll produce a net
result of water which I'll use for Waste
there and a whole bunch of more
ATP if you've had xiz class you may
remember that number is like 37 38 39
something like that ATP
and I'm left with my final end product
once I have fully metabolized carbon
dioxide or sorry
carbohydrate as
ATP
water and carbon dioxide and now I fully
metabolized a molecule of
sugar all right let's move on to talk
about fat now as I mentioned for the
most part fat is stored a little bit
different than carbohydrate so when you
have carbohydrate in your body it's
essentially stored in two forms it's
formed it's stored in the form of
glucose which is that six carbon
molecule and that's primarily when it's
in your blood so blood glucose or your
blood sugar levels now when we take that
and we store that we store that EI in
either the muscle or the liver and we
store it as glycogen what we do there is
we take a bunch of glucose molecules
pack it together and store it all right
so if I have 100 grams of glycogen that
means I literally have thousands or
millions of carbon atoms stuck together
and I can break them out as carbon
chains put it in the blood as blood
glucose well fat has a similar storage
mechanism right now what we typically do
to store fat is put it in subcutaneous
either intramuscular as intramuscular
triglyceride or subcutaneously or other
places and we call that atopus tissue we
store atopus tissue in the form of
triglycerides a triglyceride is exactly
what it sounds like it is a tri
glyceride so this means it is a molecule
that looks like an e right has a shape
like that the backbone of the
triglyceride is a three carbon glycerol
backbone so you can see here one two
three carbons glycerol and then you've
got a bunch of fatty acids so if you can
picture three to three carbons and from
each one of those carbons you attach a
big long fatty acid
chain right so you have one glycerol
backbone and One Two Three fatty acids
the length of each fatty acid determines
what type of fatty acid it is so is it a
12 carbon chain is it a 18 carbon chain
that's what's going to make it something
like steric acid or olive oil or or
different types of of oils or fats right
are determined by the length of their
carbon
chains so the first step in metabolizing
fat is to go through a process called
lipolysis in which I split a
triglyceride into its glycerol backbone
and has three free fatty acids now that
happens actually in entire system not
the exercising muscle which we'll talk
about in a second but it requires oxygen
and it is an aerobic process so I've got
my my fat and I've split it into my
glycerol and my three carbon fatty or my
three free fatty acids now what happens
here is identical so what we have to
realize is once we move past pyate and
we move down this that entire process of
metabolism is aerobic that all happens
in the mitochondria and is shifted over
so some folks fail to realize that we
actually oxidize
carbohydrates which another way of
saying when we tend to think about
oxidation or aerobic metabolism we think
oh okay uh let's see I burn fat for
aerobic metabolism and I burn
carbohydrates for anerobic metabolism
well that's fundamentally not true it is
true that you only have one option with
fat which is aerobic metabolism but
carbohydrate is started anerobic
right here to here this process of
glycolysis is 100% anerobic but in order
to finish or to fully metabolize that
Sugar molecule you have got to finish
aerobically well it turns out it's the
exact same system so once you understand
the aerobic metabolism of carbohydrate
it is the exact same as the metabolism
of fat once we split it into its
individual parts so for example the
glycerol is a three carbon chain which
means it can be treated almost
identically or exactly like pyet is so
it'll get turned into actil COA go to KB
cycle etc etc the free fatty acids are a
little bit unique and I'll skip some
steps here but they are transported into
muscle they get pushed into the
mitochondria like all the stuff is here
we're all in the mitochondria at this
level and it goes through a process
called beta oxidation in which we take
that big long 18 or 22 carbon chain and
we cut it into two carbon molecules two
carbons each this why they call it beta
oxidation then once I'm in the two
molecule form I'm a cedal COA so then I
can run through kreb cycle we go through
the electron transport chain eventually
and we make all these
ATP now as a result of that
or you uh in lie of that if we take that
fact that when we break down one
molecule of carbohydrate that's only six
total carbons but one molecule of fat is
like I said you know 20 40 60 carbons
per one molecule I'll get way more
ATP out of fat but that's a bit
misleading right we've known this for a
very long time in fact a paper came out
just last week that showed clearly if I
enhance the rate of oxidation of fat
that doesn't necessarily improve
performance in Aerobic
sports right because our our ability to
produce energy during aerobic endurance
is not limited by our rate of O rate of
lipolysis right it's it's can be limited
by a rate of oxidation but not lipolysis
so in other words I you have plenty of
of aerobic means available you have
plenty of fat available if I give you
more if I put you through a training
program or regimen that enhances your
ability to burn fat as a fuel that
doesn't necessarily mean you'll perform
better at aerobic
Sports now just to round out our picture
here let's talk about the breakdown of
of protein as a fuel source now as I
mentioned it's not a massive contributor
to exercise metabolism so it's not a big
deal but in case you were wondering kind
of essentially what happens is when we
take sugar and we pack it together we
store it and we call it glycogen when we
take fat molecules and we pack it
together we store and we call it adapost
tissue or a triglyceride when we take
amino acids together smash them together
in store we call that a protein so it's
a similar version and that's not exactly
how it works but it's pretty close so if
we take that the backwards version of
that or come back the other way with
that if we want to break down protein to
use it as a fuel source what we're going
to do is break it up into its individual
amino acids now that can actually get
broken down into a three carbon or two
carbon molecules depending on what you
do but in either case they can get
shifted and put in through metabolism
just like pyruvate or acety Co and then
you're running through the same process
so like fat protein metabolism is
entirely aerobic um for the most part so
you need to start this thing it it
requires oxygen in order to happen as a
byproduct you will also make this little
molecule called nh2 which is essentially
ammonia and this is why for years
bodybuilders have been concerned with
things like their nitrogen balance right
because it gives them an indication of
are they at a net gain or net loss of
protein right now turns out that that
nitrogen will be excreted through your
urine um which is why you can you know
you have the problems with the urine
smell of people that are on extremely
high protein diets and I mean extremely
high protein diets not just eat a lot of
protein right because it will be
excreted as
waste so you've got the basics of
bioenergetics here you've got everything
down there we're going to use this to
paint the picture or to complete the
picture that we started painting of the
real physiology of fat loss and as we
continue on we're going to start
applying this knowledge
to exercise routines so keep this stuff
in mind as we move forward now that we
understand the process of glycolysis or
lipolisis a little bit better we're
understand how we use those macro
nutrients or these sources of fuel to
produce cellular energy well it's time
to actually expand in this a little bit
so in first understand phosphor [__]
for example is purely anerobic in other
words it does not care if oxygen is
around or not it doesn't need it it's
not even required on the other end of
the spectrum over here here is fat now
fat is purely aerobic in other words it
will not happen unless you have oxygen
available and then of course in the
middle you've got carbohydrate which
doesn't need oxygen to start but in
order to finish or fully metabolize a
carbohydrate molecule you need to have
oxygen available so you've got this
Continuum fully aerobic fully Anor robic
and then carbohydrates which are in the
middle and this is one of the reasons
why being able to use carbohydrate as a
fuel is so beneficial because it can go
a little bit both ways it gives you a
little bit more metabolic
flexibility when we start to use these
fuels as an exercise we have to realize
that the phosphocreatine and the
carbohydrate are coming directly from
the active muscle but the fat is coming
mostly from the entire system so picture
yourself you're uh doing burpees right
you're going up and down and jumping up
and down touching the ground doing this
awful exercise and you just start
feeling the burn in your quads you're
using ATP and carbohydrate from your
quad in other words words the individual
muscle fibers themselves store this
carbohydrate and F this phosph creatin
in itself so it can break it down right
there send it to the Myas and and actin
and start using it to power exercise
what we don't use fat in that same
Source right what we have to do to fat
is we have to get it from the entire
body equally and this explains one of
these common myths that that most people
are aware of by now that is spot
reduction which I'll explain to you in
just a second but what we have to do say
for example as we're doing our burpees
and we start to say okay look we're
starting to run low on fossil creat in
our carbohydrate Source we need to start
using fat as a fuel source you're not
going to take fat from your Quan right
that's the idea of spot reduction the
idea that if my arms are too Flappy I'll
just work my arms really hard I'll burn
the fat in that particular spot I'll
reduce it in that area that doesn't work
that way right fat comes from everywhere
so as you're starting to burn in your
quads and you're starting to need fuel
or fat as a fuel for your quads you
start to break down fat everywhere
so the back of your neck your fingertips
your toes are on the quad area all of it
this is why when you if you've ever
known someone who's lost weight
especially if they've lost more than say
20 or 30 pounds you realize everything
on their body is skinnier not simply the
exercising muscle right if that were the
case if someone lost 80 pounds running
all the fat loss would have come from
their calfs and quads and glutes but no
it comes from everywhere right right and
did you ever think about how that
happened like how is it possible their
fingers got skinnier you think they did
a bunch of like these exercises all day
or how did their neck or jaw get
skinnier did
they in fact that's probably exactly
what they didn't do right they probably
stopped eating so much so we don't lose
fat in the exact exercising area but we
do lose carbohydrate in that area or in
this case more specifically when it's
stored in the muscle we call it muscle
glycogen all right so you can see down
here in the bottom this fat has of fuel
and I won't walk you through everything
but basically what has to happen is
you're doing your burpees your quads are
burning you start to break down fat say
from the back of your neck some adapost
tissue you've got to go through
lipolysis which is to break that
triglyceride apart into its individual
body parts put it into the blood we have
to transport that fatty acid through the
blood and we have to attach it to an
albumin molecule it's got to move it
around then we got to get it transported
into the muscle cell in this case our
quad it's got to go through the quad
muscle and get uploaded and put into the
mitochondria it's got to go through the
membrane there once we do that we have
to go through that beta oxidation and
then the cycle and then we finally get
some
ATP well we do get a lot of ATP or
energy from one fat molecule but do you
see how long can you imagine how long it
takes relative to Simply using the
carbohydrate that's right there right so
there's pros and cons to both systems
here more energy from one but it's much
slower right much faster over here but a
lot less total energy and I only have a
limited Supply right the the typical
physiology thing we teach is the average
say 77 kilo man who's maybe 20% body fat
has probably enough fat on their system
to power them to 30 to 50 straight days
of
exercise right your fat will never be
your limiting factor but your
carbohydrate absolutely can because you
can only store so much of it in your
cell and it turns out your body doesn't
really care about maintaining the amount
of fat you have on you it's your backup
storage it does care about maintaining
blood sugar though and muscle
glycogen all right so here's what it
basically says if you run blood sugar
low or muscle sugar muscle glycogen
levels low we will use our fat stores to
replace
that right I'm not going to let you walk
around with low muscle glycogen if I
have any energy available possible
anywhere right but if you lose a little
bit of fat go up a little bit of fat and
we don't really care so it's not a major
concern of
it what's the Practical implication or
application of all this information well
I'd say twofold number one people are
far too concerned about making sure they
work out the exact muscle that they want
to lose the fat from like spot reduction
now what they also were too concerned
about is which macronutrient I'm using
or I'm
burning when I'm working out as we
talked about earlier and I think we've
made this point by now it all comes out
as carbon dioxide anyway so it doesn't
necessarily particularly matter if
you're burning fat during your workout
or you're burning carbohydrate your goal
is simply burn carbon dioxide I will
explain to you this later on the video
why that exactly makes sense and I'll
connect some dots but before we get
there what I want to do is walk you
through what I call the circle of carbon
life this will help put in context the
exercise and the nutrition
piece to understand my understand my
schematic here what you have to see is
in the top hand corner anything you see
that is green are things that happen in
your physical body the things that are
in the blue area in the atmosphere and
things in the yellowish brownish color
or things that are in plant well let's
remember that in our body what the way
that we store fat and sugar are chains
of carbon okay now in your blood you
store Sugar blood as glucose that's a
six carbon molecule but then when you
pack that away and you store it in your
muscle you call that muscle glycogen if
you have too much of that floating
around too often your body will say look
our muscle glycogen levels are packed or
full let's store all that extra sugar as
fat same thing will happen if you
overeat protein or fat right doesn't
that's not necessarily specific to
carbohydrate my but they're they're
structurally very similar similar fat
and carbohydrate storage so fat adapost
tissue carbohydrate is muscle glycogen
which is a big chunk of
carbons or blood sugar well what happens
is like we talked about earlier you've
got these big CH long chains of carbon
you go through your workout about
whatever it happens to be you do your
Jane Fonda your Pilates or your
intervals or whatever you want to do you
breathe in O2 you breathe out CO2 like
we talked about earlier and so now that
lonely little carbon molecule has found
its oxygen buddy and it is out in
space
well we as humans breathe in O2 breathe
out CO2 and when we breathe out that
means we're literally losing one of our
stored carbon molecules but what we know
about plants is they do the
opposite right we know this right trees
particularly are important because
they're the ones that give us our are
breathable O2 they breathe in
CO2 hold the carbon and breathe out O2
and because they held carbon the length
of their carbon chains get bigger and
bigger and bigger so they get taller and
taller we as humans don't have the
ability to extract carbon from the
atmosphere but plants do so since we
can't do that we have to get our carbon
from other places which is the
plants okay so that same carbon molecule
that was your fat pad that you that is
now in the air as CO2 is consumed by a
plant they hold on to that molecule they
tack it onto their carbon chain it gets
longer now just like in your body when
we have sugar floating around we store
it as muscle
glycogen plants do the same thing and
when we store it in Plants we don't call
it muscle glycogen since plants don't
have muscles we call it ready for this
drum
roll
starch right that's all starch is folks
it is the muscle glycogen equivalent for
plants right so if we take a a plant or
a vegetable like a potato we know that
potatoes are very high in starch which
means they have taken all of the sugar
all of the carbohydrate made it as sugar
and packed it away as these glycogen
molecules
essentially right so when we now ingest
that that potato it goes into our belly
as a potato it gets broken into its
individual carbon diox or carbon
molecules we put it in the blood as six
carbon molecules called glucose which is
why starches raise blood sugar levels
but they do it over time because they're
densely packed we it takes us a while to
break down all that glycogen into
smaller chunks of glucose fruit on the
other hand is more like fructose or
fructose which is a six carbon chain
it's one of your simple sugars but it's
the same thing so when we ingest those
things they raise our blood sugar levels
really fast or quickly because they're
already in that identical form that six
carbon form
right but nonetheless my point is
starch is essentially the plant
equivalent of muscle glycogen and
fructose or glucose in fruits and things
like that are essentially the same thing
as your flooded glucose so you ingest
that plant those fruits those vegetables
into your belly right so now that same
carbon
molecule is back into you right because
some of us don't necessarily realize
that the macro macro nutrients in plants
is carbohydrate when we eat meat we
generally get protein when we eat other
sources um nuts and things like that we
get mostly fat but plants and vegetables
are all
carbohydrate which for the record if you
haven't heard this yet before
carbohydrates and sugar it's the same
word right so yes fruits are full of
sugar which is just carbohydrate and
that's not necessarily inherently bad
for you but what happens if you over
inest sugar
or over inest carbohydrate or over inest
fat for that matter since it's just
carbon your body says we're stored here
pack it in and store it away as a fat
molecule if we're out of muscle glycogen
space so hopefully that helped you
understand a little bit the connection
between the carbohydrates you eat the
fat you eat the fat you burn the
carbohydrates you burn and we can move
on to our next
concept have you ever been to a gym and
seen a chart like this right what this
is supposedly telling you use the cardio
zone right so depending on your age what
you can do is use your heart rate to
determine where your max fat burning
zone is well this is a real problem
people don't understand this chart what
this chart actually shows you is a very
poor understanding of exercise
physiology that by now hopefully you
understand what what's wrong with it so
here's the general
myth you need to work out at somewhere
between like 60 and 70% of your maximal
heart rate
to burn the most fat now what this is is
a trick of percentages and I'm happy
because most gyms are going away from
charts like this because it's incredibly
deceiving we talked about this a little
bit earlier can you lose fat if you work
out at 60 to 70% of course but you need
to work out for a very long time because
that doesn't require a lot of breathing
and we're not ex exhaling or getting rid
of a lot of CO2 but that what that
doesn't mean is I have to work out in
that zone to maximize fat burning
because maximizing fat burning is not
necessarily maximizing fat
loss just because I'm using fat as a
fuel doesn't necessarily mean I will
lose more fat so let's dive into that a
little bit and I've come up with a
couple of examples just to highlight the
idea so this is a concept that's very
important and it's really the foundation
for that chart so that chart is
technically a little bit correct but in
application is totally wrong let me walk
you through this chart to help you
understand this concept so what you're
going to see here is a red line which
will represent the amount of calories
that you're getting from or the energy
you're getting from fat the black line
will be what you're getting from
carbohydrate and what we'll do is we'll
see how that changes when we're resting
when we're doing some easy exercise Hard
Exercise all the way out to maximal
exertion so with the black line here for
carbohydrate what we see is at rest
maybe 40% of the energy you're getting
is coming from carbohydrate with the
other 60 or so coming from fat okay now
that number is debatable but it doesn't
matter it's something like an even split
maybe 70% fat 30% carbs something like
that as you can increase the intensity
of your exercise you start working
harder and harder and harder the
percentage of your energy that's coming
from carbohydrate starts to go a up and
in fact at maximal exertion 100% of the
energy is coming from carbohydrate and
that makes sense because if you think
about a little bit earlier we talked
about when we use carbohydrates for fuel
it's it's coming from the exercising
muscle and we use fat it's coming from
everywhere else and when we're
exercising at a maximal intensity I
don't have the damn time to wait for fat
so I'm going to say screw it I know I
don't get as much bang for my buck here
but the I'm using only the carbs I have
which means how long can I possibly go
at maximal exertion not long right until
you have to start slowing down which is
for the record why you slow down is
because you don't have enough time to
bring in the fat and use it as a fuel so
your body says slow down give us some
time well when we know that turns out
the exact inverse is happening with fat
so again at rest it's something like a
split but as you start to exercise a a
lower and lower percentage of your
energy starts coming from fat because of
what we just described so people use
this to then say okay if I want to
maximize my fat burning therefore my
workout intensity should be
something extremely
light and and I understand that I
sympathize with people that think that
because it doesn't make sense you might
be thinking hey well if I Max if I work
out in this hard or even Max exercise
region I'm not burning fat as a fuel and
that's right you aren't therefore I
won't lose
fat my counterargument to this would be
this if that's the case you know what
the the what type of exercise you could
go do or what activity you could go do
that would maximize your fat burning
it would be this like ghost space go
take a nap that's when your heart rate
would be the lowest the percentage of
energy you're using coming will be the
highest coming from
fat now no one in the right mind thinks
that if you just lay around and sleep
all day and lay on the couch that you'll
lose fat so clearly something's broken
down with this logic of lower the
intensity increase the fat
burning so what's really happening here
it's a little bit of a game of numbers
and I've made some up to help you
understand this idea and don't worry
about the exact numbers I'm trying to
highlight the concept I think you've
gotten the point already that you need
to move and breathe so if we took a look
and we compared three different activity
levels so the first would be resting so
you're sitting here watching this video
the next would be if you ran a 15minute
mile which for most people is kind of
hard but not too hard or you run a 5
minute
mile and let's say percentage wise where
did your energy come from let's say at
rest you are burning 2/3 fat a third
carbohydrate for a total of 100% okay
fine doesn't matter and let's say during
that 15 M mile or that 5 minute mile you
burned 100 T calories and without
getting into the details here yes you
heard that correct you'll burn the same
amount of energy roughly it's just one
will take you three times as long okay
so you burn equal amount of
calories well if we look at our
percentages here 66% or 67%
um of our energy coming from fat at rest
well as we start to exercise those
numbers start to get lower and so maybe
33% of our energy at a moderate level
exercise comes from fat and 2third of it
comes from
carbohydrate but when you compare that
to the 5 minute mile like I said 100% of
it's going to come from carbohydrate so
you might be thinking aha like I said
run the 15minute mile and you will
technically burn more fat okay so if we
compared our 15 minut Mile and our 5
minute mile who burned more fat well you
might think the 15minute mile burned
more fat and technically you'd be
correct but my counter argument would be
again who cares both cases you burn 100
calories and that's what
matters right so who burn more calories
it's identical in fact you could even
probably argue that the five minute mile
would burn more than 100 calories based
on energy and displacement and things
like
that but the real question is who lost
more
fat well in order in order to understand
this we have to keep going right because
fat loss would probably be about the
same between the two but one of them
spent three times the amount of time and
if you've ever worked with a client or
yourself if you've ever missed a
training day like I did yesterday
sorry why is it right what's the number
one PE reason people either don't work
out or they skip training sessions I
don't have time so if we want to talk
about physiology ology that's not
necessarily the same thing as Behavior
so I would argue that okay you might
technically burn more fat with the
15minute mile it's going to take you 15
minutes or 45 minutes the other way will
burn you the same or maybe even more
calories but will take you a third of
the time and I promise you right now if
you took a client you said look I can
get you to lose 20 pounds in two months
do you want to work out three times as
long or a third as long for the equal
results they're going to say a third
right most most of the
time so I want to finish this by going
back to the beginning right remember
when I said all those things end up as
CO2 anyway so regardless if I'm burning
fat or carbohydrate it's coming out as
CO2 and so anything that makes you
breathe makes you lose
weight still kind of confused haven't
really put all the pieces together maybe
thinking
again I think I get it but I'm not
really buying in because I need to look
fantastic in my bikini
let me walk you through this the last
little piece here because we understand
the structure of a fat and carbohydrate
what we now can realize is that it is
very easy for your body to convert a fat
into a carbohydrate so here's really
what happens you go do your intervals or
you do that ski urg or whatever you have
to do and you do that high-intensity
exercise that is technically burning
zero fat
right and all you're burning is
carbohydrate meaning you burn down half
of the muscle Al glycogen in your
quad if you don't consume a huge
carbohydrate diet right you're not
eating something obnoxious you're not
overe eating hundreds of carbohydrate
calories a day and by the way I'm not
saying you have to go on a low carb diet
I'm just saying you're eating a normal
reasonable mixed macronutrient diet if
that's the case your body will say hey
look we've got all this extra fat Ling
around but we are low on muscle glycogen
and because as I mentioned earlier it
cares more about preserving blood sugar
and muscle glycogen levels your body
will break down the fat it has converted
into sugar and replenish your muscle
glycogen so although you technically
only burned carbohydrate during the
workout you will burn fat in order to
replace the muscle glycogen and that my
friends is how I can lose fat by only
doing high-intensity
exercise so can you do low intensity
exercise and lose fat absolutely if you
burn fat you going to lose some fat but
you don't have to right just get carbon
out whether it comes from a a a anerobic
or aerobic exercise means it's okay
either
way all right so try super hard burn as
much muscle glycogen or sugar or carbs
as you possibly can and let your body
use the fat stores you have to replace
the muscle sugar
so which is best right should I do some
sort of steady state endurance you know
running cycling swimming for an hour
what about maybe something like strength
training heavy lifting or how about
something like circuit training um maybe
some intervals and different things like
that well it turns out again it comes
down to a little bit of
adherence what we have to understand is
this nutrition is King when it comes to
weight loss you can only do so much from
the exercise side of it I love these two
articles that came out you can see them
here the first one is debunking the myth
that exercise is an effect of weight
loss
treatment another one a similar one is a
paper that came out this and I won't
read you the title but basically what
these things argue is that exercise
itself only provides you the minimal
amount of what you need to actually lose
fat now this is not saying exercise
doesn't work or you shouldn't exercise
or you don't have to exercise trust me
it will make your fat loss way more
successful if you do a lot of really
hard work but what it is saying is this
a bad diet will beat out your great
workout program any day and you can read
these papers but I'll give you the very
highlight is what the last one in
particular is suggesting is that
evolutionarily it makes sense that your
body will actually conserve energy
output so in other words you go through
a super hard workout and burn a thousand
calories the rest of the day your body
will downregulate energy expenditure by
a th000 calories so that your day daily
energy output is
identical so whether you worked out or
not you'll burn 3,000 calories that day
all right for every calorie you burn
working out your body will Throttle Down
the rest of the day now this is far from
a proven scientific thing but this was
published paper and is an interesting
thought been some stuff to refute it to
say that doesn't happen but what it does
help people realize is that most of
weight loss comes from your diet okay
we'll have separate videos to talk about
that because exercise is important so
let's focus on what we do know about the
exercise one specific benefit of
exercise during fat loss is that it
enables you to preserve muscle mass
while losing fat all right this is
critically important and I'll spend a
few minutes talking to you about why
exactly that is so first of all if we
take a look at what's actually
happening when you exercise I like to
think about exercise adaptations being
falling into five separate categories
speed power strength hypertrophy and
conditioning well if you look at this
list you don't see fat loss on this list
you may be thinking am I trying to tell
you that fat loss is not an adaptation
to
exercise well what I'm saying is it is
not a direct adaptation but it is a
byproduct and what I would probably say
is it falls somewhere under these two
Realms or sort of Two and a Half Realms
right in other words what I'm saying is
if you program for hypertrophy and if
you follow the guidelines for
conditioning those two things will
result in a lot of fat loss and that
bracket may even stretch a little bit up
into some of the basic strength training
stuff you're probably not going to lose
a lot of fat doing what's traditionally
referred to as speedwork or power work
and I'm not going to get into the
details of what that means in this video
you'll have to check out one of the
program design videos I will give you
some specific recommendations for what
it means to do strength hypertrophy and
conditioning work a little bit later in
the video but suffice to say if you do
those or some sort of combination of
those those are probably going to help
you achieve your fat loss the most which
is again trying to help you maintain or
even gain some lean body mass while
losing some fat Mass right if this
didn't matter we could all just go on a
starvation diet we would lose fat we
would lose a lot of muscle but we would
lose a lot of weight right that's not
really what we're looking for we're
trying to preserve muscle mass or
slightly enhance it and why this is so
important is we've known now for the
last decade or so thanks to the
Fantastic work by a Scandinavian
researcher named Mente
Pon that skeleton muscle is more than
about Aesthetics and performance it's
what we call an amino acid Reserve in
other words it's the place on your body
that holds all of your extra amino acids
now why this is critical is because
amino acids are the building blocks to
proteins proteins are of course your
skeletal muscle and things like that but
they're also the backbone of your immune
cells they're the backbone for your
hormones for your hair for your red
blood cells for your
kidney so what's happening is if we have
sufficient muscle mass we have the
ability to store extra amino acids so
when we have some sort of insult injury
sickness we're able to quickly create
the antibodies we need to attack prevent
and cure our illness all right and you
can see from the graphic here you can
see the schematic uh of a skeletal
muscle and you see the contraction and
we now know that contraction causes the
release of things called inter lucans
these IL sixes right these IL sixes
speak directly to your fat Mass right
and you can see in this particular case
it's activating lipolysis it's also
speaking directly to things like your
kidneys and liver telling it hey convert
glycogen to glucose and put it in the
blood or it's telling you to do other
things it's uh can be inflammatory
anti-inflammatory Pro pro-inflammatory
it can enhance fat oxidation
right depending on what it's doing what
I'm really saying here is muscle is
actually in fact the biggest organ in
your body right in fact you can probably
Wikipedia this and if you just type in
what's the biggest organ in your body
you're probably going to hear something
like your skin well it's totally true if
you ever go on Jeopardy or something
that's going to be the right answer but
the reality of it is the right answer is
skeletal
muscle it speaks to other things we
thought for years that skeletal muscle
was stupid in other words central
nervous system tells skeletal muscle
what to do do it just do it just does it
now what we finally understand thanks to
the phenomenal work by Dr Pettis and
other people like her is that skeletal
muscle is talking back in fact it's
probably driving the boat on most of the
things happening in your body one way to
think about this is that your brain is
your central is your control center but
your muscle is your
factory if you have adequate factory
size you're able to ship parts around
the country right your manufacturing is
fine you can handle changes in
production
but if you don't have your your factory
under control you're not able to make to
make quick responses to things so just
to be very clear here what I'm not
saying is if you're 6 feet tall you're
22y old male and you're 220 lb and you
bulk up to 230 lbs you're not going to
get any healthier you're not going to
lose fat any faster but if you are a
client or working with a client who is
doesn't have sufficient skeleton muscle
adding on some skeleton muscle to them
can be extremely beneficial for them for
their fat loss in fact one of the first
things that we do with clients is put
them on a little bulking cycle or a
little hypertrophy cycle to make sure
they have sufficient muscle mass so that
they have the ability to create these
signaling molecules and mechanisms that
tell their body to stop storing
fat another way to think about this is a
phenomenal article I like and I didn't
make this up this is actually
legitimately the title of the article
this was published in cell metabolism in
2008 but this article is called bulking
up to slim down I love the graphic that
the authors put together in this paper
because I think it illustrates our Point
very clearly if we look at skeletal
muscle hypertrophy and probably very
specifically fast twitch skelet muscle
hypertrophy what we see is the
relationship between skeletal muscle and
cellular function in the rest of our
body so as our first tab over here we
can see now we understand that skeleton
also controls things like glucose levels
right so you're working with someone
who's having a hard time regulating
blood glucose one of the questions that
you can ask yourself is do they have
sufficient a well functioning skeletal
muscle now I'm certainly not saying if
you just put some muscle on some people
that cures all their diabetes or
anything like that but I I will say it's
an important mechanism other look at the
other things that skeletal muscle can do
it directly talks to atpo cells and
helps regulate the size of atpo cells
again remember atpo cells are your fat
tissue it can do things like reduce
glucose
uh play with with insulin and leptin and
other things that regulate energy
storage or energy use uh increase fat
oxidation at the uh at the liver or
other things so I think it's really
important that we take this stuff and
understand that if we're talking about
fat loss probably putting somebody on an
hourong running program every day is not
the most effective program can work and
maybe should be a component but probably
not the most effective we probably need
a more well-rounded program that
includes things like a little bit of
hypertrophy work I guess what I'm saying
is if I had to create a hierarchy of
exercises that help me burn fat it would
probably look something like this at the
bottom of our pyramid would be the
things that are probably the most
effective and then that should occupy
the majority of our training and to me
those are activities that are short but
require Max or near maximum breathing
right something that makes you huff and
puff a lot think intervals here on top
of that that probably not quite as
effective but still very effective are
things that help you build muscle um
this would be more high volume
resistance exercise more repetitions
probably shorter rest intervals things
that make you burn quite a bit increase
respiration a lot but also challenge a
lot of muscles specifically on top of
that are things that are a little bit
longer but require medium breathing and
then probably things again that are
effective but probably least effective
especially when we consider per unit of
time in other words bang for my buck how
long how many hours a day do I have to
do on top of our pyramid would be things
that are long and require little
breathing now I'm personally of the
opinion that variety is key here so you
probably should use all of these things
but the bulk of your program maybe half
of your workouts or more should be down
probably in this area either things that
are bulking or or helping for
hypertrophy and skeletal muscle or more
interval based approaches or some
combination like
that and and I think if we look at the
literature it supports this quite a bit
I love this paper this was published in
the strength and conditioning journal
from Dr Mike Stone Mike is a legendary
Sports scientist and he took this
actually from the Olympic Training
Center in 2006 so what he did is took
all the Olympic athletes that were
getting prepared for the Olympic Games
and he wanted to look at how many
calories per kilogram per day they were
actually burning and what he noticed is
when he broke it up across all the
sports that were at the Olympic Training
Center there wasn't really much of a
difference between the caloric
expenditure of all the
athletes now this is pretty crazy to
think right if we asked most people and
in fact maybe if I asked you this said
who do you think is is going to burn
more fat a cross country Runner or an
Olympic thrower like someone that does
the javelin of the shot put well most
people would think it's way higher
you're going be hundreds of thousands of
more calories for the cross country
Runner and and it could be but if we
break it down per kilogram of body
weight it's not that much
different same thing is true by the way
for females when we looked at when Dr
Stone looked at the females of the
Olympic Jer he saw a similar Trend
numbers are a little bit lower but that
makes
sense physiologically but the point is
here the
overarching understanding here is that
exercises themselves do not determine
the adaptation in other
words the exercise you pick to do in
your program to help you or your client
lose fat is almost Irrelevant in fact it
is completely metabolically irrelevant
the
application of the exercise determines
the adaptation so how you do the
exercise determines whether or not it
will be effective at fat loss I'm not
really specifically talking about
exercise technique here of course that's
clearly important what I'm talking about
here are things like how long did you do
it for how intense was the workout how
many repetitions did you do how much
physical work did you accomplish so when
it comes to selecting the actual
exercise if you love running by all
means run if you hate running or if you
have bad running technique you do not
have to run a step in your life to lose
100 pounds right pick meet meet your
clients here if you're working with an
athlete pick an exercise that they
really really like a movement that they
like that they can perform thousands of
repetitions that that they'll feel safe
that will they will let them let
themselves challenge themselves on right
that they won't be hesitant about and
then program that a lot give them a lot
of movement variety but don't program
them to do complex exercises that they
are they're uncomfortable with or that
they don't know how to do or they have a
technical limitation with because when
you start doing a lot of repetitions
kind of heavy for with low rest
intervals or for a long time that that
poor technique or that self-limitation
is going to make them not do nearly as
much work or they're going to get hurt
right so the actual exercise you pick to
do is almost Irrelevant in terms of
physiological calorie burning what's
more important is how hard you work and
how often you're going to do
it this is probably why I get so
irritated or I'm so amazed when I see
things on Twitter or Facebook that are
stupid uh clickbait things like you know
top three exercises you have to do to
lose weight or best ways to trim your
belly what exercise do I do to lose that
awful fat on your my stomach I it's
complete nonsense pick the exercise you
want to do you're technically sufficient
at that you like doing the more variety
the better but the exercise itself
really doesn't matter in fact if you
were to actually Wikipedia this and I
don't know if this is still up but the
last time I did if you Wikipedia things
like aerobic
exercise you would get a list of
exercises which is crazy to me because
like I just said exercises do not
determine adaptation application
determines adaptation so what makes an
aerobic exercise it has nothing to do
with the exercise choice you select what
makes it aerobic is the way you do it so
if I want to go if if I went to this
aerobic exercise page on Wikipedia I
should be being told how to perform the
exercise or how to do the movements it
doesn't even matter which movements I
pick right now if we were to pull a
crowd of all the people in your gym or
or all your all your friends or your
family at your last family picnic and we
just ask them a simple question like hey
do you think all the pictures over here
do you think that's all fat burning
exercises they would all all probably
say absolutely that's what I need to do
to lose weight right in fact if you were
to go to the doctor and depending on how
old you are you may or may not have been
to the doctor
but imagine that you have or you know
someone that's been to the doctor with a
little bit overweight and the physician
says something like you know hey Bob
you're you know you're really getting
overweight I'm going to need you to
start exercising I'm going to need you
to get out there and get on that
treadmill right I need you to start
going for I need you to start running or
get on a bike or start swimming why are
they telling me what exercise to pick
they need to be telling me how to do it
this is how long you need to do it this
is how hard uh this is what I recommend
in terms of your rest intervals how
frequent a week you're some basics of of
technique if you choose these exercises
instead of just giving me a list of
exercises now I would agree with you and
your family that I would certainly say
that those are pretty good exercise
choices to make if you're trying to
program fat loss but I would also say
what about things like
this right I mean look at these poor
ladies look at their faces do you think
that their heart rate's not extremely
elevated right of course it is what's
their ventilation look like are they
breathing they're doing a TR mendous
amount of work to me this falls into the
category of excellent exercise choices
to help lose
fat in fact I would even stretch it out
to go in farther say what about things
like
that what about a deadlift depending on
how you're doing it in terms of again
how many repetitions how many sets
you're doing it how frequently you're
doing it this can absolutely be
effective at stimulating or promoting
fat
loss in fact I won't go too far down the
rabbit hole here but I'm I'm really
fixing ated on this and I would love to
do an hour talk on just this slide right
here maybe let me know if this is
something you'd be interested in but it
brings about a really interesting
discussion
about what are some of these terms we
constantly use in the weight room and in
the classroom for example what does
aerobic exercise really mean what
exactly is cardio and what is resistance
exercise I challenge you right now come
up with the definition of these things
I've been doing this for years in my
classroom and I've still never had
anyone succeed it's really really hard
to Define what resistance exercise is
for
example right is it uh anytime you're
working against
gravity no I'm doing that right now no
one would really consider what I'm doing
right now to be resistance
exercise is it anytime you're working
against an external load well again a
pull-up right some people can't use
anything more than their body weight for
a pull-up there's no added load there
but we would consider that to be
resistance exercise so it's really
challenging on the aerobic or cardio
side of
it right would you consider a one
repetition maximum deadlift
cardio most people wouldn't and I
certainly wouldn't but what's that mean
cardio means cardiovascular you ever
taken your heart rate after a one
repetition deadlift I guarantee you it's
through the roof but yet we don't
consider it to be
cardio right now aerobic you could say
it's has to do with oxygen but I promise
you right now ain't nothing you could
ever do you won't use oxygen
for so those things get really really
challenging I guess what I'm really
saying with all this stuff is to hell
with it don't worry about it it's
minutia you're playing colloquial games
about things that honestly don't matter
for you or your client right stick to
the basics here another way to think
about this problem is look at the
pictures on the top of the
screen right these are traditionally
anerobic exercises and they are things
that people associate with stuff that
you do if you're playing a sport or if
you're young but if we think about
things that you do for your health we
tend to about think about pictures like
this at the bottom and so for whatever
reason we have this really skewed system
that anerobic exercises are things that
you do if you're a sporting young
athlete and aerobic exercise is
something you do for your
health it's completely misguided another
way to think about this is hey lifting
is something I do for muscle if I want
to look good or play football well I
want to train my muscle I go lift I want
to train my heart I go
run that's absolutely fundamentally
wrong that is no way is how your body
works right lifting absolutely is a
cardiovascular
challenge I promise you cardiovascular
is also a muscle challenge so we have to
get ourselves out of this mentality that
that's how things work I promise you if
you can do that your programs will be
800,000 times more effective you'll keep
people healthier they'll get to reach
their goals a lot longer and they'll
stay with you uh for forever because
you're going to have these basic
fundamental understandings I guess what
I'm really trying to say with all of
this is that when you're talking about
designing your workout programs to make
sure you achieve fat loss it comes down
to three things number one you got to
get work done pick whatever exercise
whatever duration whatever days a week
multiple days a week one day a week
intervals rep ranges all you got to
focus on is getting physical work
accomplished number two you've got to be
consistent right the work's got to be
done and number three be patient if you
do all those things I'm almost going to
guarantee you exercise wise you'll have
a sufficient program as long as you're
not overworking people that's going to
help them achieve all of their fat loss
goals now I know that that's not good
enough for you so I don't want to leave
you without giving you some very
specific recommendation for design
numbers again we'll talk about specific
recommendations for food and calories in
a bunch of other separate videos so
let's start with hypertrophy I want to
walk you through some of the very very
basics of program design when we're
talking about hypertrophy especially
considering or with the idea that we're
doing hypertrophy for the purposes of
fat loss eventually so some basic
concepts here to pay attention to
generally pick complex movements and you
want to have a very fairly equal balance
around each joint so don't do all
horizontal pressing or all hinging or
things like that you want a well
balanced movement around the joints you
probably want to pick somewhere between
about three and six exercises per day uh
and somewhere between like three and 10
total sets per muscle group this can be
highly varied but I'm just giving you
some very basic fundamental starter
guidelines and now generally we
classically say uh hypertrophy is
optimized between 8 to 10 repetition per
set um but this number can be widely
varied you're you're welcome to go down
to five repetitions or even as high as
20 to 25 but for the most part stick
between like maybe eight and 15 reps per
set something like that you're going to
want to do this pretty heavy though
right in order to to hypert muscle you
need three things you need metabolic
challenge you need muscle tension um and
then you need some sort of minimal
amounts of muscle damage right so the
muscle tension here is what you're going
to get with our heavy load 70ish to 90%
right it's got to be kind heavy um for a
beginner or a novice athlete you may
even slide that down to 60% that still
might be pretty heavy for him but the
goal would be to start working your way
up to higher things all right uh now
you're probably not going to be doing
three sets of 10 at 90% that's really
high so if you're doing set of 10 or 12
you're probably more like 70% if you're
doing set of five you might be closer to
90% And then at the very bottom there
you want to do maybe two to three um
times per week each Muslim so that
should give you some basic guidelines
for hypertrophy if that's what you're
focused on now in terms of the method
they're infinite all right so the way
that we like to talk about this is the
concepts are few but the methods are
many so you know you can do things like
vertical pressing bent rows deadlifting
squatting horizontal pressing lots of
core and torso and stability work and
through there but one thing I do want to
caution you against is minimizing
weightlifting movements so if you're a
weightlifter and what I mean by that
specifically is Olympic weightlifting
you don't want to necessarily do
snatches clean and jerks or any of their
variations uh for sets of 8 to 10 to 12
right I'm not saying you can't ever do
it or some Advanced athletes can't do it
but as a general rule for the purposes
of fat loss there's Simply Better
exercises to pick all right they're
fairly complex there's a higher injury
risk when the load is really heavy and
you're doing a lot of reps and you're
really tired right it can be done but
just probably not the greatest choice
now you could do something like a snatch
grip deadlift that's fine um you just
don't want to make the comp the
movements too complex especially when
they're throwing and catching things
over their head of course overhead
squats those type of variations um
totally fine the same thing with
Plyometrics so these would be jumping
and Landing drills you don't necessarily
do these things for the sake of
hypertrophy so three sets of 10 of box
jumps is not really something that's
going to put you in your optimal
hypertree range again you can but for
most clients most people it's not what
we're really looking to
get from there I like to break this up
into my next category so if you remember
earlier when I said there's five basic
adaptations so speed power strength
hypertrophy and conditioning I actually
like to break up conditioning into three
separate subcategories Anor robic
aerobic and then long duration we'll
start here with the anerobic
conditioning our basic concepts are as
follows we still want to pick complex
exercises you know the basic Point here
is we want to work a lot of muscle
groups at the same time this saves
actually physical time so I don't have
to be in the gym so long also the more
muscles I'm using the more work I'm
doing I'm accomplishing my goal of
achieving work right producing work so
complex movements um this doesn't mean
things like one-f footed on a ball where
I have to Twist by complex I mean big
muscle groups a lot of them moving at
the same time you know something like a
deadlift which is pretty simple but
still in this category would be
considered complex because you got a lot
of muscle moving a lot of parts are
going all right so complex movements or
exercises probably something like 1 to
10 exercises per day so you don't need a
lot of variation in your exercise per
day here it could be one right uh your
aerodine a classic exercise choice for
this stuff maybe a Prowler sled right
maybe you just that's it maybe you use
only the prowler push or a sled drag is
your only exercise choice for your
anerobic conditioning for that day now I
would still encourage you to have
multiple uh different exercises
throughout the week especially if you're
not a competitive athlete if you're just
doing this for the sake of fat loss to
enhance variety making sure that you
don't get overuse injuries um by doing
the same movement pattern over and over
again that's what I mean when I say
balance per week probably somewhere
between three and 15 sets per day again
this can be wildly variable depending on
exactly what you're doing but the
intensity needs to be at something like
at or above your V2 Max this quite
literally means it's Anor robic right so
something that makes you get really
really really hard now if you don't know
what your V2 Max is don't
worry this is something like you know 80
90 95% or higher of your max heart rate
right don't have to measure it you don't
have to put a heart rate monitor on just
go as hard as you can right if you feel
like you're going to throw up that's
probably pretty good you know you don't
have to go to 99% you're probably going
to get equally equal weight loss out of
92% as you are
97% um so just work hard be safe but
work hard now what makes anerobic
conditioning specific
is this work to rest ratio now this can
swing anywhere from something like 3: 1
all the way out to 1 to5 but the key is
the duration of the exercise is probably
somewhere between five and 60
seconds now I'm trying to be very soft
on all these recommendations because
there's no magic here there's nothing
that says 61 seconds is not Anor robic
conditioning or you can't go 4 to one or
1 to six right I'm just giving you
ranges to generally play in so let's
make this work to Restoration IO example
very very easy say you did something
like 30 seconds of work as hard as you
can with 30 seconds of rest 30 to 30
means a one: one work ratio with 30
seconds of work that falls perfectly in
our Anor robic conditioning right you
could also do things like I did with my
friend Mike McGoldrick very recently
where we did 10 seconds as hard as you
can but 50 seconds off and then you do
that for 10 or 20 minutes that would be
like a 1 to five work ratio so 10
seconds work 50 seconds off or you can
go the other direction and do something
like maybe 30 seconds of work with 10
seconds off right now there's pros and
cons to those they are quite different
but the point is you're getting a lot of
work
done okay then lastly for our Concepts
is you probably want to do about two to
five different um different times per
week to do this with your novice people
maybe the most that can handle is is two
sessions a week like this you got a
highly trained athlete or at least an
experienced exercise
you might be able to pull this off five
times a week but I'll would say your
average person in fact the research is
shown quite clearly twice a week for as
little as four week can show significant
improvements in fat Mass so maybe two to
three times a week is probably a good
number to shoot four
here in terms of the concepts I
mentioned this or I alluded to this a
little bit earlier ago uh excuse me in
terms of the methods you can pick but
you got a lot of variety here you could
use kettle bells or dumbbells or you
could do some sprinting uh rower a sled
basically any exercise that allows you
the confidence and Technical ability
tactical ability to go as hard as you
possibly can for some sort of short
duration all right again we're going to
we're not really going to use
weightlifting or PL metrics in this set
because the risk factor generally again
we can be used but what I'll also add to
this one is a little bit of a pro tip
try to select excises that are primarily
or if you can only
concentric now understand what I'm
saying here concentric versus Ecentric
so concentric is when the muscle
shortens Ecentric is when the muscle
lengthens so for example when I am
pushing a
Prowler I'm not Landing very much on the
ground I I put it on my my foot on the
ground softly and then I push hard I
concentrically push as opposed to
something like a jump where I land and
have to absorb that Landing if you do
this I promise you you will never be
sore in your life well maybe that's not
true but you'll be tremendously sore I
want you to do 30 on 30 off five rounds
of this and I want you to do vertical
jumps so for 30 seconds the want you
jump as high and as fast as you possibly
can for 30 seconds take 30 seconds break
and do it
again come back tomorrow tell me you're
not ripping sore right Ecentric actions
make us really damn sore so if you do
that at this volume at this intensity
you're going to kill your clients only
young healthy 22 25 year old athletes
are going to be able to handle that the
rest of the population is going to get
crushed and never come back for five
weeks all right so pick things like a
rower which again there's no absorbing
there's no Landing in a rower there's
only pushing they same thing with a sled
or a bike or an aerodine you can work
your ass off with those things and
you're not going to be tremendously sore
from them because there's no landing and
absorption right you catch a bunch of
front cleans or cleans in the front
squat position you're going to get
pretty sore
there in terms of aerobic conditioning
it's very very similar to Anor robic but
essentially what we've done is stretched
out the Tim length of the work right so
again we want to do complex big
important movements probably only going
to do one to three exercises per day
you're not going to really do a bunch of
variety here within the day but you do
want to balance this throughout the week
maybe something like one to five sets at
or equivalent to your V2 Max
did I catch you right there all right a
huge mistake people make here is
thinking aerobic conditioning is
submaximal and that's not true if you
want to challenge your maximal aerobic
capacity you have to work at your
maximal aerobic capacity aerobic
conditioning is not easy it is not sub
maximum this is at your V2 Max or again
at your max heart rate or something like
that we'll get to the submax stuff in
just a a second your work to rest ratios
probably makes more sense to be
something like 3:1 to 1:1 you're
probably not going to do like 2 minutes
of work and then rest 20 minutes and
it's going to be like a seven hour
workout so maybe something like 3
minutes as hard as you can one minute
off or 10 minutes as hard as you can 10
minutes off maybe something like um if
you've ever done a one mile repeat so
run a mile as fast as you can take that
exact amount of time off and then do it
again and do three or four or five
rounds of that you want to lose some fat
mou oh my gosh this aerobic conditioning
stuff is brutal you can probably only do
about two to four times per week again
because this is a lot more challenging
than the Anor robic conditioning stuff
it's just a lot more volume right it's
tremendous amount of work exponentially
more work being done here your beginner
athletes maybe once a week your your B
beginner clients um even your Advanced
folks maybe maybe twice a week is still
still enough in terms of the methods
that you select to actually get this
stuff done just like the last slide very
similar anything you can do maximally we
want to minimize the weightlifting
movements absolutely minimize no jumping
here minimize landing and stay
concentric for as long as
possible okay so now that we've
described anerobic conditioning we've
described aerobic conditioning the last
thing that I'll put under the
conditioning Banner is what I'll call
long duration conditioning some people
call this long SL long slow um I hate
that term but it's long duration
condition
so this is any movement really tends to
be more simplified movements because you
have to do it longer um so something
like running maybe cycling on a bike
these are fa fairly simple um small
muscle mass movements it's probably one
exercise uh per day you're not doing
multiple exercises per day but you might
have a couple of different exercises you
choose from each week it's one set it is
sub maximal this is not to say it is
less effic or less effective all right
I'm not down playing it here I'm I'm not
minimizing it it's continuous work
though it's probably 15 minutes or more
of steady state for the most part work
right uh probably up to even 30 45
minutes up to an hour for most people
but even an hour is stretching it I
think 30 to 45 minutes is a good number
you could probably do this fairly
frequently uh it's not too too dangerous
or too hurtful on the body if your
movement is good if you move well right
so if your running technique is good you
want to emphasize sort of Moder just
slow reps because you want to be able to
make it for 30 minutes you don't want to
have to stop at 12 minutes and be done
the idea here is to sustain and to not
stop at all so your basic movements are
the same anything you can do for 15 more
minutes that you're technically and
tactically capable of doing of course
this eliminates weightlifting it
eliminates Plyometrics for the most part
and again we want to try to stay
concentric running is the big banger
here right if you if you aren't used to
these types of things do not do not send
a client out to run for 45 minutes don't
even send them out to run 20 minutes if
they're not used used to it their quads
are going to be crushed the next day
because of all the Ecentric
Landing earlier I listed patience as one
of my three important keys to successful
weight loss well what allows people to
be patient through this process is
having a realistic understanding of how
fast the weight loss is going to
actually occur so I wanted to show you
what this should possibly look like and
to give you some successful weight loss
tips right first and foremost it's trial
and error now this is true for the
exercise program stuff with we talked
about here but it's also true for the
nutrition there is not one system that
works for everyone and that's what's
even crazier is there's not one system
that works for every one person right
the same program the same exercise the
same habits that worked one time or to
help you lose the first 20 pounds maybe
won't help you lose the last 10 I
remember giving seminar a few years ago
and there was a lady in the stand she
asked me a great question and she said I
you know I look I just lost 65 lbs the
last year and she was maybe 20 30 lb
overweight at the time said I lost 60
lbs already but I've been at this
Plateau for like the last 5 months and I
said oh man you know that's first of all
that's great but um well what have you
changed in the last five months and she
said well
nothing said what do you mean she's like
well you know I lo lost the first 60
pounds following this exact program and
I didn't want to change it well it
worked for the first 60 but it's not
working anymore so we've got to change
things all right so you got to make sure
that this is always a p a process there
has to be some sort of energy deficit
right we talked about that there's got
to be less carbon coming in than there
is carbon going out all right so this is
probably best with a combination of
excess carbon going out via exercise and
less carbon coming in Via less food now
I'm not saying less
carbohydrate uh although that is one
option I'm just saying less food in
general so you should aim for a caloric
deficit of something like 10 to 15% do
not make huge cuts in calories I worked
with a gentleman years ago was probably
450 lbs and we met for the first time
and I said all right walk me through
what you do what your normal day looks
like Nate this is the no judge Zone here
just tell me the truth and so he said
well you know on my way to work I pull
over at of course the fast food
restaurant and I get two egg McMuffin
sandwiches or something uh and orange
juice and hash browns I said okay well
tomorrow let's try to make a change and
he said yeah so tomorrow I'm going to go
there instead of getting my two Egg
McMuffins my hash browns and my orange
juice I'm going to get half a hash brown
and the orange juice and a bite of one
of the egg
sandwiches and I was like whoa whoa whoa
whoa that's like an 85% cut in calories
that's a horrible idea what I want you
to do is go from two egg sandwiches hash
browns and orange juice two orange juice
hash browns and one and 3/4 of an egg
sandwich right 10 to 15% is the most
you're going to get away with I promise
you I've done this a
lot right in terms of the weight loss
you should be shooting for something
like losing about a half to 1% of your
body weight per week which for most
people is usually like a pound to a
pound and a half per week that's
probably a a good number for long-term
sustained weight loss not rapid weight
loss for two weeks to make weight for
competition but if you're working with a
client who's interested in losing weight
over time if they are tremendously big
again you're 300 pounder your your 50%
body fat uh you might lose two to three
pounds a week but that's really really
rapid even a half a pound per week is a
good number right what's sort of
interesting I always tell people of you
know what if I came up to uh your friend
or you yourself and I said hey I
guarantee you I can get 20 pounds off
you in the next year or I can lose you
40 pounds in two years people would be
like damn I oh my God I would love to
lose 40 pounds and they'd be happy but
if you said Hey what if I can guarantee
you a half a pound a week or one maybe
one and a half to two pounds a month
they're going to be like get the hell
out of here terrible I'll pay somebody
else
right so people have a hard time
grasping that number but I'm telling you
this is the realistic number of what's
going to be successful long term a quick
note on nutrition I would recommend that
you do not minimize carbohydrate unless
you're under special circumstances but
you might play on the moderate to lower
end of your carbohydrate
recommendations all right um make sure
that you m maximize protein or keep that
very very high as well as your minerals
and your vitamins fat and carbohydrates
are the one you could probably play with
with right so if you want to go a little
bit lower carb or a little bit lower fat
you don't want to eliminate either um
generally unless you're going on a very
specific diet plan which you can do
there are some out there that are
effective but for the the average person
just get them on the moderate to lower
end of the recommendation for the
carbohydrates keep protein high or
higher keep minerals and vitamins and a
bunch of other things like that really
really sharp and then lastly make sure
that they can enjoy food and have a
social life again if we're trying to
talk changes in habits over time changes
in lifestyle you can't cut out your
friends you can't cut out every piece of
cake or glass of wine or every
cheeseburger the rest of your life and
mo for most people that's just not going
to work I realize there are some out
there that can do that I'm actually
fortunate I can I don't have a hard time
really with that um but most people
that's not going to work in fact most
people when you restrict like that it
makes the problem even worse so to put
my money where my mouth is I wanted to
show you some of the things that I've
actually done
myself so this is the chart of my body
weight um getting ready for national
championships and weightlifting in oh
probably
2010 something like that I can't
remember exactly maybe a little bit
before wait no more like 2007 I I can't
remember but here's the point I started
off at about almost 180 pounds and had
to get to 151b so that was about 28 lb
or so I had to lose you see I started
out here in the end of December and had
to get to that weight by by um
essentially get all the way down to my
weight by I think I had July or
something like that well I cut off the
chart just to make you think but what
you can see here is if you look at my
chart you can think man you're so smart
you have a PhD you lost weight perfect
everything went great you had this
linear loss of weight but that's not
what happened at all in fact look at
that time frame right there from January
12th to March 9th I came into January at
something like 175 lbs and I walked out
of March at like 173
lbs right and you can see look at the
day-to-day variations I mean I'm all
over the place here I knew I had a long
time so I wasn't being tremendously
strict I was just trying to be good
knowing that look overtime because I
started really early I'm going to get
down to where I need to be eventually
right so what's happening with you or
most of your clients is if they're
frustrated and they're not losing weight
you're probably
zoomed in too far
right if you zoom into this graph right
here you're like ah [__] two months or a
week and a half or something and my plan
didn't work but if you zoom out far
enough that weight loss line starts to
look like a perfect linear
decrease right so again zooming in that
picture there and you're like oh my gosh
you're not losing any weight you're at
the same weight but when we zoom out
everything looks all hky
Dory in fact you can even knew a few
days over here where uh some bad things
happen turns out there's something
pretty awesome that happens towards the
middle of Janu or the middle of April
there my birthday all right so maybe we
had some problems there may have been a
Vegas trip in there or something like
that I can't really remember okay so be
patient you're playing the long game
here you're playing the big picture I
want to end this episode of 55 minute
physiology by going all the way back
this is one of my favorite books of all
time this is galin's hygiene if you
don't know who he is he's one of the
fathers of physiology or certainly of of
exercise physiology some would give him
that credit but this book is phenomenal
if you ever get a chance to read it and
what I've done is I've actually taken a
passage out of it I want to read it to
you because I think it just blows my
mind how well he understood physiology
thousands of years ago so let me walk
you through
this quote to me it does not seem that
all of movement is exercise but only
when it is
vigorous right so just because you're
moving around just because you take the
stairs or you park a little bit further
away in the parking lot that doesn't
necessarily make it exercise it has to
be vigorous this is the difference
between physical activity and
exercise but since Vigor is relative the
same movement might be exercised for one
and not for another so for me to park at
the end of the parking lot and to walk
into the exercise and into the store uh
giving me five or you know 20 extra
steps that's not necessarily exercise
for me but for some folks that might be
enough so keep that in mind one of the
best pieces of advice I can give a young
trainer or a coach is to not project
your abilities and your uh skill set
onto your clients have some empathy and
sympathy for what they're able to do and
make sure you really pay attention It's
probably hard especially when you're
young for you to realize what's it feel
like when you're 55 years old right so a
out that you think it's not bad for me
it might be exhausting for them so it's
relative so let's keep that in
mind going back to the book The
Criterion for Vigor vigorousness is a
change in
respiration those movements which do not
alter the respiration are not called
exercise so you want to know what's a
quick way to tell you're exercising does
it change your respiration or not right
I love this when you go to the gym and
you see people on the elliptical and
they're reading magazine right they're
on the stair stepper probably not the
stair stepper that one's kind of hard on
the treadmill whatever it happens to be
on the bike right Cruis around the bike
if it doesn't change your respiration
it's not
exercise but back to the book here if
anyone is compelled by any movement to
breathe more or less faster that
movement becomes exercise for him or
her now according to Galen he says quote
the uses of exercise I think are twofold
one for the evacuation the evacuation of
excrements what he means there actually
is not like those kind of excrements not
like going to the bathroom but he means
by losing fat we are trying to
evacuate the
excrements all right and I'm not going
to sufficiently evacuate extrs if I'm
not raising
respiration beautiful right he got this
whole carbon in carbon out thing
thousands of years
ago quote and the other is for the
production of the good condition of the
firm parts of the body I don't mean
those firm parts of the body he's
talking about muscle here
hypertrophy fat loss that's why you
exercise most
people and
finally quote and from the vigorous
movement of
respiration the Ducks must be purged and
the excrements can be evacuated in other
words breathing out
CO2 I hope you enjoyed this installment
of 55 minute physiology I know this was
a bear hopefully I inspired you to go
look up some other things to go explore
exercise physiology and biochemistry
stay tuned for next time if you got any
questions of course let me know on
social media Instagram Twitter you know
the drill Facebook post it up here
anywhere you have to do um let me know
if you have any thoughts or questions I
thank you for staying along uh staying
along for the ride for this long and
we'll see you next time